《异形魔怪5：血脉》
我叫毕甘默
My name is Burt Gummer.
我有很多外号
And I've been called many things.
枪狂
Gun enthusiast,
怪兽猎人  末日预备者
monster-hunter, doomsday-prepper.
我拒绝这些标签
I reject all these labels.
我是生存者
What I am is a survivalist.
我走遍内华达州和墨西哥的沙漠
I've scoured the dirt and dust of Nevada and Mexico,
冒着生命危险  搜捕一种巨型地下怪物
putting my life on the line to hunt super-size subterranean
他们以吃人为生  名叫圭布
man-eating predators called Graboids.
我利用我对本地的认识  直觉和炮火
Using a combination of local knowledge, intuition and firepower,
成功地将这种致命生物
I've managed to control this deadly species,
限制在北半球
and keep them confined to the Northern Hemisphere.
加入我
Join me.
跟我进入这死亡沙漠的地底
As I enter into and beneath the Sands of Hell.
下午3点
1500 hours.
穿越这完美的沙漠王国  内华达
Moving through the desert of Perfection, Nevada.
和圭布埋身肉搏
Ground zero for war with the Graboids.
如果你是新来的  对圭布一无所知
For those of you newcomers, who don't have a clue about Graboids,
圭布
Graboids
让我向你解释下
let me bring you up to speed.
圭布是一种邪恶的地下猎食者
The Graboid is a vicious subterranean predator,
大概9米长  有半硬化的内部构造
about 30 feet in length with a semi-rigid internal structure.
他能感受猎物的震波
It senses its prey seismically,
从口中伸处三条  像蛇一样的触须
and employs three powerful, snake-like oral tentacles
捕获猎物  将其塞入食道中
to ensnare its prey, and pull it into the Graboid's gullet.
那里可不好玩
It is not a pleasant venue.
相信我  我到过那里
Trust me. I've been there.
如果这还不够  圭布还会  生出三只叫史力的丑陋幼兽
If that weren't enough, Graboids give birth to three ugly spawn we call Shriekers.
他们很矮  看不见东西  用两只脚半蹲着行走
Short, squat, and blind bipedal bad boys
用生物红外线探测并捕杀猎物
that sense and hunt their prey using infrared sensors.
他们又会生下艾巴
These, in turn, give rise to the Ass Blaster,
一种有翼的食肉兽
a winged, predatory carnivore
他们会从肛门中喷出
which uses a mixture of volatile chemicals in its...
一种化学混合气体
...nether regions
利用这冲力升上空中
to blast into the air and swoop down upon its victims.
艾巴生下的蛋  卵孚化后变成新的圭布
Ass Blasters carry eggs that hatch and become new Graboids,
开始新的地狱轮回
beginning this hellish cycle anew.
我和圭布  史力和艾巴交手无数
I have survived a great many skirmishes with Graboids,
并生存至今
along with their Shrieker and Ass Blaster kin.
这令我具独一无二的资格
And that makes me uniquely qualified
教你面对他们时  如何生存
to teach you how to survive whatever life throws at you.
记着  生命和生存
And remember, life and survival
从这里开始
starts here.
谁饿了
Who's hungry?
(人类的摇篮)
(南非)
你在做什么
What're you doing?
收声
Shut your blow hole.
我在追踪
I'm tracking.
你感觉到吗
You feel that?
你唯一能感觉到的是  我一脚踢你屁股
The only thing you're gonna feel is my boot in your bum.
看你那条瘸腿怎踢我
Yeah, good luck, with that gimp leg of yours.
这地方很无聊
This place is gut boring.
是的  我又饿又累
Yeah. And I'm tired, and I'm starving.
我们在这一整天  只看到一群土狼
And the only thing we've seen all day is a pack of spotted hyena.
这是自然  兄台
Yeah, it's just the nature of things, boet.
说到自然  我要送孩子们去泳池
Yeah, well, talking about nature, I'm gonna drop the kids off at the pool.
向西北看  在高原后
Looking northwest, over the Highveld.
报告说发现很多奇异动物
All those reports about exotic animals,
这里没有野生动物
there's no wildlife here.
说到野生动物
Well, speaking of wildlife,
不知我老婆会否回到我身边
I wonder if my wife's gonna come back to me.
如果她有脑的话
If she's got brains,
绝对不会
definitely not.
你这无可救药的蠢材
You're a complete and utter idiot.
我很痛苦
I mean, I'm hurting here. I'm in pain.
你却嘲笑我
And you mock me.
比臣  你听到吗
Basson. You hear that?
我什么也没听到  我在开会
I didn't hear anything. I'm in conference.
就在这里  这里
It's right here. Here, here, here, here.
比臣
Basson?
德亚
Dreyer!
你掉得很深
That's a long drop.
你没看到这洞吗
Didn't you see this gigantic hole?
我想我摔裂了屁股
I think I broke my butt.
我去找条绳来
I'm gonna grab a rope.
兄弟
Bro!
我来了  老友  放松
I'm coming, man, relax.
- 比臣 - 在
- Basson? - Yeah?
我扔绳子下去  你抓住它  我拉你上来  好吗
I'm gonna throw this rope down. You grab onto it, I'm gonna pull you up, all right?
快点  下面有些东西
Hurry up. There's something down here.
好的  抓住绳子
Okay, grab the rope.
救我出去  这里有些东西  快拉我上去
Get me out of here, there's something down here. Just get me out of here.
是的  可能是我前妻泰蕾莎
Yeah, probably my ex-wife, Teresa.
拉
Pull!
好的  你也帮帮忙  来吧
Yeah, just help me out man, come on.
你得减肥了
You need to lose some weight.
救我出去  我濑尿了
Get me out of here. I'm pissing myself.
比臣
Basson!
(莫哈维沙漠)
(内华达南部)
41.6摄氏度
107 degrees Fahrenheit.
你好吗  内华达
Hello, Nevada.
耶
Oh, yeah.
在野外一切都更好味
Everything tastes better outdoors.
但如果你想在这享受  营养丰富的美食
However, if one wants to enjoy a source of sustenance out here,
就要大胆些
one has to seize the culinary initiative
将丑陋的生物变为美餐
when it rears its ugly head.
我们来看看
So, let's review.
我用50分钟搭建起这土炉
It took me 50 minutes to build this improvised clay oven.
32分钟来生火
Thirty-two minutes to fire up the scrub wood,
加热内部
heat the interior,
将蛇放进去并封好口
feed in that snake and seal the door.
现在我们就等他们  变为美食佳肴吧
Now we wait as this little baby turns snake into snack.
很热
That's hot!
好了
And voilá!
热辣辣  美味多汁  富含蛋白质
One sizzling, succulent piece of pure protein.
然后加入毕的劲好味牌  仙人掌汁腌料
And you can bet that Burt's Bullseye Brand Cactus Juice Marinade
令这变得更惹味
will eradicate any trace of that
保证不会像鸡肉
"tastes like chicken" residue.
你他妈是谁
Who the hell are you?
耶
Yowza!
闻起来像鸡肉
Smells like chicken.
这就是他
There he is. Huh?
神秘的传奇人物
The man, the myth, the legend.
毕甘默  我是卓华斯韦加
Burt effing Gummer. Travis B. Welker.
对不起  先生  我该早些通知你
Sorry, sir. I should've told you that.
我无意跟踪你  但我是你忠实拥护
Don't mean to be all stalkery, but I've been a big fan of yours
自从看了你2000年的阴谋论剧集起
since your Y2K conspiracy series.
我可以收工了
Well, I guess that's a wrap.
不要擅离职守  莱利  还没到休息时闲
Maintain position, Riley. It's not Miller Time, yet.
他是你的了
He's all yours, buddy boy.
你的设备在那边
Your gear's piled over there.
多谢那工作
And thanks for the Vegas gig.
什么工作
What Vegas gig?
拉斯维加斯娇妻
The Real Housewives of Las Vegas.
你不能这样抛下我
You can't just adiós on me!
这是工会的工作  有退休金和医保  所以...
It's a union gig, pension and health. So...
这是你新的摄影师
That is your new camera guy,
他口碑很好
and, well, he comes highly recommended.
经验丰富
Lots of time in the eyepiece.
你擅离职守  老友
You're officially AWOL, mister.
我想你没看过我履历
So, I take it he didn't give you my resume?
我有些东西给你
All right, I got something for you here.
这是我的数码履历
This is called a digital file.
能充分展现我的实力
It's gonna speak to my awesome capabilities.
真希望你的网页也能做到
Kind of wish your website could do the same for you,
但我能帮你
but I can help.
你说什么
I beg your pardon?
我是你的拥护  可能是最忠实的
I'm a big fan. You know, possibly your biggest.
你置身内华达州  这个无人关心的地方
But the fact that you're out here in Who-The-Hell-Cares, Nevada,
到处是响尾蛇
smokin' rattlesnake says something.
你知这说明什么吗
You know what it says?
你埋没了自己  老友
It says you're underachieving big time, my man.
你该成为全球品牌  来吧
You should be a global brand. Come on!
你认识几个怪兽猎人
I mean, how many monster-hunters do you know? Huh?
我只认识一个  毕甘默
I know one. Burt Gummer.
你有多少个Twitter关注者
Last check, how many Twitter followers did you have, huh?
零
Zilch.
你的好意我心领了
Your opinion is duly noted.
我来这里就是为了  帮你打造毕甘默的品牌
It's what I'm here for. To help build out the Burt Gummer brand.
这名字如何  "多疑独行侠遇上魅力神经刀"
I'm thinking, "Paranoid loner meets charming whack job."
我可以帮你解决问题
I can fix you.
我不需要人解决问题
I don't need fixing.
你有什么问题  老友  看太多《绝命毒师》
Yo, what happened to your dome, my man? You binge watch Breaking Bad, again?
要吸引年轻观众群  就要加入饶舌音乐
You trying to appeal to a younger demographic, get a little Pitbull on us?
我有什么问题与你无关
What I choose to do with my cranium is none of your business.
好吧
All right.
这是蛇对吧  不是老鼠
This is snake, right, not rat?
哇
Whoa!
真惹味  甘默出品  必属佳品
That is a win. That's a yummer from The Gummer.
你该暍瓶啤酒
You know what, you look like you could use a cold one.
我要  你呢
I know I can. You want?
我想我们相处融洽  对不对  老爹  你感觉到吗
Hey, I think we're vibing right now, right, Pop? You feel it?
谈得很投契  你的啤酒呢
It's good talk. Where's your beer?
唏
Hey.
不要碰我的装备
Hands off my gear.
放松点  老爹
Lighten up, Pops.
你是政府的人
You from the government?
不  佛州人
Nope. Florida.
在墨西哥湾沿岸长大
Grew up on the Gulf Coast.
巴拿马城  坦帕  彭萨科拉海湾
Panama City, Trampa, Pensacola.
- 彭萨科拉  - 是的
- Pensacola? - Yeah.
他们有个不错的枪展
They got a great gun show.
是的  就在洲际公路旁
Yeah, right off the Interstate.
我74年去过那里
I was there in '74.
我看出来了
You got that look.
看出什么
What look?
你在佛罗里达做过一些  见不得光的事情
The "I did some dirty things in Florida" look.
我明白  那是70年代  爱情自由  你还年轻
Hey, I get it. It was the '70s, free love, you were young.
现在怎样
What now?
看来税局终于找上门了
Looks like the IRS finally caught up with you.
甘默先生  甘默先生
Mr. Gummer. Mr. Gummer.
你简直神出鬼没  先生  实在太难找
You are way off grid, sir, you're a very difficult man to find.
显然还不够难找
Evidently, not difficult enough.
我叫艾力云韦
I am Erich Van Wyk.
来自南非野生动物部
I'm with the South African Wildlife Ministry.
南非  你是政府的人
South Africa? You with the government?
什么  不  我是你拥护
What? No, no. I'm a big fan of yours.
继续说
Go on.
我们在豪登目前处于危机
Well, we have a rather pressing situation in Gauteng.
豪登  人类的摇篮
Gauteng. The Cradle of Humankind?
是的
Yes, that's right.
我们确认目击到  你称为艾巴的怪物
We have a confirmed sighting of what you would refer to as an Ass Blaster.
这不可能  这种生物  只在北半球出没
That's impossible. The species are confined to the Northern Hemisphere.
这种正在南非造成恐慌的怪物
Oh, well, then, I suppose it's some other flying carnivore
我想是一种屁股喷火  而且会飞的食肉兽
that shoots flame out of its rear end that we have wreaking havoc in Africa?
你们确定有人看到
Is this a confirmed sighting?
是的  先生  但目击者已经死了
Oh, yes, sir. Although the witness is no longer alive.
- 我们何时出发  - 很好
- When do we leave? - Excellent.
慢着  亚甘
Slow your roll, there, Gums. Okay.
你这非洲人真会说话  云迪先生
You're quite the fetching bushman, Mr. Van Dick.
是云韦
It's Van Wyk.
云韦  好吧
Van Wyk, right, okay. Um...
甘默先生不再涉足怪物界
Mr. Gummer really isn't in the monster business, anymore.
什么
I'm what?
我能和他谈谈吗
Give us a minute, will you?
你在做什么
What the hell are you doin'?
我要从这人身上捞些好处  好处
I'm working this dude for some paper. Paper?
钱  听着
Cash. Listen.
你不能接受第一次开价  我帮你讨价还价
You don't take the first offer. Let me close this deal.
我拒绝  我独自工作
Request denied. I work alone.
但你需要一个摄影师  对吧
Come on, but you need a videographer, okay?
你要看长远些
You need to take the long view on this, okay?
你想想  甘默在非洲
Think about it. The Gummer in Africa.
这是个好机会  将你  做的事记录在影带上
This is our chance to catch you on tape really doing what you do,
看你如何对付艾巴
and really giving it to those Ass Blasters.
你懂我意思吧
Okay, that came out weird, but you know what I mean, right?
这世界很残酷  你只是新人
This is real world, son. You're a newbie.
新人
Newbie?
先不要扮大哥  听我说
Okay, stop being Burt for a second, and just listen.
我可能没花半辈子时闲  和巨型怪兽搏斗
I may have not spent most of my life fighting giant, blind worms,
但我过去10年都身处危险区域
but I spent the last 10 years of my life deep in the shit.
帮国际新闻网络和霍士电视  在沙漠上拍片
Pulling gigs for CNN and Fox in the sandbox.
我去过阿富汗  叙利亚  你知道那些地方吗
Yeah, Afghanistan, Syria. You know those places?
知道
Yeah.
说到武器
And as for firearms,
我新入手这宝贝
I just added this baby to my collection.
HK  91
HK 91.
- 你从哪里得来的 - 啊啊啊
- Where'd you get that? - Uh-uh-uh!
你批准我跟你去南非
You punch my ticket to South Africa,
我便亲手奉上  这漂亮的半自动机关枪
and will I hand over this beautiful, semi-automatic Mr. Shotty to you.
成交
Deal.
艾力  我能叫你艾力吗
Erich. May I call you Erich?
当然
Of course.
我们很感谢你的邀请
We really appreciate your offer,
但甘默先生打怪兽的日程  已经订满了
but Mr. Gummer's monster-hunting schedule's all booked up.
对不起
Sorry.
真可惜
Oh, uh... That's a pity.
到奥扎克打大脚怪
Bigfoot in the Ozarks.
到弗雷斯诺打妖精
Possible gremlin in Fresno.
听说在秘鲁还有狼人
Family of werewolves in Peru we heard about.
打扰你们了  两位
Thank you for your time, gentlemen.
虽然我想这不会  改变你们的主意
I don't suppose it would make any difference
但如果我提出赞助
if I offered to fully fund
甘默先生未来两年的影片拍摄呢
Mr. Gummer's videos for the next two years?
四年
Four.
三年
Three.
航班何时飞
What time does your plane leave?
你们多快能收拾好
How quickly can you roll your tents?
已经好了
Rolled.
毕甘默要来南非了
Burt Gummer. In Africa.
非洲不是胆小鬼来的地方
Africa's not for sissies, yeah?
我们吃自己捕杀的猎物  兄台
We eat what we kill here, boet.
我能叫你兄台吗
You mind if I call you boet?
兄台  就是兄弟的意思
Boet? Yeah. It means brother.
你是怪兽猎人
So, you're the monster-hunter?
是的
Yeah, somethin' like that.
这不像我之前见过的艾巴
This doesn't look like any Ass Blaster I've ever seen.
- 莫名吸引  - 什么
- Strange attraction. - Come again?
一个猎杀怪兽的男人  具有莫名的吸引力
A man who hunts a monster. It's a strange attraction.
比维先生  你醉了
Mr. Bravers, are you drunk?
还没有
Not yet.
甘默先生
Mr. Gummer?
我们要去河南岸  一间野生动物园木屋
We're heading for a safari lodge, just south of the river.
屋主很慷慨地让我们  将那里作为行动基地
The owner's been kind enough to let us base our operations there.
唏  我从美国带来的装备和武器呢
Hey, where's my bug-out bag and the weapons I brought from home?
说到这个
About that.
南非的入境条例非常严格
We have very strict customs laws here in South Africa.
我应该提醒你  枪械要经过三天检疫隔离
I should have warned you about the three-day weapons quarantine.
三天什么
Three-day what?
别担心  我准备了一批武器
Don't worry about it. I've procured us some weapons.
在木屋里
They're waiting for us at the lodge.
就在那里
There, there it is, there, there.
(摇篮石保护区)
(马利斯山脉)
做得好  云戴
Nice digs, Van Dyke.
是云韦
It's Van Wyk.
- 唏  兄台  - 什么事
- Hey, boet. - Yeah?
我要告诉你一个故事
I got a story for you.
在非洲  每天早上  当一只蹬羚醒来
Every morning in Africa, a gazelle wakes up.
他知自己要跑得比最快的狮子快
And he knows he's gotta run faster than the fastest lion,
否则...
otherwise...
他会被杀死
He gets killed.
每天早上  一只狮子醒来
Every morning, a lion wakes up.
他都知自己要跑得  比最慢的蹬羚快
And he knows he's gotta outrun the slowest gazelle,
否则他会饿死
otherwise he's gonna starve to death.
因此不管你是狮子还是蹬羚
So, it doesn't matter if you are a lion or you're a gazelle,
在非洲  每当太阳升起
in Africa, when the sun rises,
你就要跑
you better be running.
唏  如果你需要帮忙  吹这号角找我
Hey, if you need my help, call me on the horn.
- 你保重  兄台  - 谢谢
- Now, you go well, boet. - Thank you.
快点  老爹
Chop-chop, Pops.
不要再叫我"老爹"
Stop calling me "Pops."
好吧
Got you.
老鬼
Old man.
我们安全了
And we're clear!
什么  我不明白
What? I don't understand.
这是一个震波监测仪
This is a seismic vibration monitor.
和南非国家地震网互联
It's uplinked to the South African National Grid of Seismology
能探测到80公里范围内  圭布的移动
and can detect Graboid movement within a 50 square-mile area.
高科技
Next level type stuff.
圭布  大虫  没错
Graboid? Worms? Exactly.
这位是庄拿德亚
This is Johan Dreyer.
他是我的地方代表人及  该区的野生动物园导游
He's my local field representative and a safari guide in the area.
他是致命袭击的目击者之一  没错
He's the one who witnessed the fatal attack. That's right.
而这一大块朱古力是我助手塔巴
And this towering hunk of dark chocolate is my assistant, Thaba.
你们这枪真犀利
That's quite a gun you got there.
来福
Rifle.
一定令你觉得自己充满力量
Bet it makes you feel like you got a lot of power.
我可以在100米外打死一只犀牛
I can drop a charging rhino at 100 meters.
你想试吗
You wanna go for a run?
你是冲锋飞车队的
How's life in the Thunderdome?
犀牛用角刺穿你的喉咙
Well, you wouldn't know what a rhino looked like
你还不知他长什么样子
if it shoved its horn through your throat.
任何已知的镇静剂  对圭布和艾巴都不起作用
Graboids and Ass Blasters are immune to any known form of tranquilizer,
对我们正追捕的生物  一般的武器毫无用处
rendering your weapon useless against the creatures we're hunting.
你们计划活捉他们吧
Capturing. Capturing, that's the plan, right?
你不能活捉他们  只能猎杀
You don't capture these things. You kill them.
杀死  活捉  我不管
Kill them, capture them, I don't care.
但我们非洲没有圭布  先生
But what we have in Africa, sir, is not Graboids.
如果你们有艾巴  就有圭布
If you've got Ass Blasters, you've got Graboids.
(普华斯湖挖掘点)
(豪登省)
有齿生物
Odontotermes baadi.
是的
Yes.
但体型庞大
But on a massive scale.
他有同样的镁下牙
It has the same magnesium mandibles.
解释了基岩附近为何有蚁酸
That explains the presence of formic acid in the bedrock surrounding it.
他吐出酸  软化岩石  下牙就能皎穿它
It spits out the acid to soften the rocks, while the mandibles chew through it.
这是超级挖掘兽
This is a super digger.
我们会上《科学》杂志封面
We're going to be on the cover of Science magazine.
我上过了  宝贝
Been there, baby.
我要上《国家地理杂志》
I want National Geographic.
甘默先生  甘默先生  这边
Mr. Gummer. Mr. Gummer. Over here.
真爽
Can you say, "Ballin'"?
祖鲁语"爽"怎么说
Hey, what's the Zulu word for "Ballin'"?
你好  巴鲁提  带孩子们去散步
Hello, Baruti. Taking the kids for a walk, I see?
那些年轻女士太高贵  看不上你这样的人
Well, you know that these young ladies
总得有人来做
are too high-class for the likes of you, so, I guess somebody has to do it.
自然点
Just act natural.
他们是来调查闪电鸟袭击的
These men are here investigating the impundulu attack.
怪兽猎人  对吧
Oh, right, the monster-hunters, right?
算是吧  我还在培训
Ish. I'm still in training, but I got, like, a credit away.
这里
There.
你要枪  亚毕  这就是我们的枪
You want guns, Burt? This is how we roll.
哇
Wow.
我看看
Here you go.
这是什么
What's this?
你要的枪炮
The weapons you asked for.
一支BSA  303和一支  30-06
A BSA .303 and a .30-06?
还有一支柯尔特
Well, there's also a Colt Peacemaker.
和一支...
And a...
双枪管长枪
Ooh! The double-barrel thingy.
你开玩笑吧  我们还得  用锯将它分开
Are you serious? We might as well use a spit straw.
不是所有请求都会获批
Granted, it's not everything you requested.
不  我只要被你们的  慈居政府爪牙没收的枪械
No, what I requested was confiscated by your mindless government lackeys.
是的  我很抱歉
Yes, I'm sorry about that.
他们不会向每个
They don't just hand out machine guns
来这国家的驯兽师发机关枪
to every jacked-up safari jockey that comes to this country.
这是非洲  甘默先生
This is Africa, Mr. Gummer.
但我们不全是野蛮人
But we're not all bushies.
这是种族歧视吗  听起来像
Was that racist? That sounded a little racist.
原始人
Bushist.
你答应会给我足够的枪械
You promised me adequate weaponry.
你以为我们在追捕什么  会飞的松鼠仔
What do you think we're hunting, Rocky, the flying squirrel?
30-06能打倒非洲任何生物
That .30-06 will drop anything on this continent.
任何
Anything.
这是谁
Who's this?
唏  嗨
Hey. Hi.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
电死虫子做饵
Zapping worms for bait.
看  他们来了
Look. Here they come.
顶
Damn!
你有芥辣吗
You got any wasabi?
吃吧
Eat it.
- 吃  - 这是非洲传统
- Eat it? - Eat it. African tradition.
这真是非洲传统
Is it really African tradition?
- 不  - 噢  老天
- No. - Oh, God.
卓华斯  卓华斯
Travis, Travis.
这位是娜蒂莫塔布医生  这保护区属于她
This is Dr. Nandi Montabu. She owns the reserve.
你好  医生  娜蒂就好
Hey, Doctor. Nandi is fine.
不  有免费无线上网和咖啡店才叫好
No, free Wi-Fi at a coffee shop is fine.
你就像假日饮品
You are like a holiday drink.
就像一杯焦糖玛琪雅朵南瓜味拿铁
Like a caramel macchiato pumpkin spice latte,
除了你不是南瓜味  是非洲香料味
but instead of pumpkin, it's African spice.
好吧  听来很美味  谢谢  你一定是卓华斯
Okay, well, sounds delicious. Thank you. You must be Travis.
放松点  韦加先生
At ease, Mr. Welker.
甘默先生  欢迎
Mr. Gummer, welcome.
我在木屋后为你们  准备了一些点心
Um... I've arranged some refreshments for you back at the lodge.
- 非常感谢  医生... - 是娜蒂
- With all due respect, Doctor... - It's Nandi.
娜蒂  我想我们  该马上出发捕猎
Nandi, I think we should get right to the hunt.
我们先休息  甘默先生  明早才行动  好吗
Let's rest up, Mr. Gummer. Start fresh in the morning, yes?
我们不是来参观动物园
I'm not here on a safari weekend.
如果圭布在这里  人人都不安全
If you've got Graboids, no one is safe.
卓华斯  你吃了那些虫子吗
Travis, did you eat the worm?
你好
Well, hello.
我们做到了
We did it.
你做到了
You did it.
我讨厌回到现实世界  对着那些吸毒上脑的学生讲课
Yeah. I hate to go back to the real world and lecture at stoned-out students.
能留在这丛林里  和你一起真好
Be nice to stay out here in the bush, with you.
我希望这一刻能永远持续
I wish this moment would last the rest of my life.
这是比臣死的地方
That's where Basson died.
- 坐标  - 什么
- Coordinates? - What?
什么  经度和纬度
Longitude and latitude?
我不用坐标
I don't do coordinates.
一切都记在我脑里
Everything is in my head.
实地通讯呢
What about field communications?
- 这是什么  - 猴子婚礼
- What the hell was that? - A monkey's wedding.
本地的说法  太阳雨
Local lingo. Sun shower.
每年这个时候  每天同一时闲都会发生
We get them every day, at this time of the year, at the exact same hour.
你能按这个校表
You can set your watch to it.
下午3点  没错
1500 hours. Exactly.
大自然母亲有她的节律
Mother Nature keeps to her rhythms.
莫塔布医生  娜蒂  怎么
Dr. Montabu. Nandi? Yes?
我想你们想看这个
I think you guys might wanna come and see this.
为什么
Why?
发生另一起袭击
There's been another attack.
艾巴绝对不会这样做  云韦先生
An Ass Blaster definitely didn't do this, Mr. Van Wyk.
唏  亚甘
Hey, Gums.
你也许想看看这个
You may wanna check this out.
蠢材要付出血的代价
If you're dumb, you bleed.
你的问题比我想象中严重  云韦先生
Your problem is bigger than I thought, Mr. Van Wyk.
为什么
How so?
这圭布比美国的大得多
This Graboid is much larger than the North American variety.
这是非洲  一切都更强大
It's Africa. Everything's bigger.
除了我的武器
Everything except my munitions.
知己知彼方能百战百胜
Knowing your enemy's strength is Intel 101.
你还有什么惊喜给我
What other surprises do you have in store for me?
我也在学习中  甘默先生
I'm learning as I go, Mr. Gummer.
这只很长  长得多
This one's leaner, too. Much leaner.
更危险
And more dangerous.
我们需要一只巨大的笼子
We're gonna need a big-ass cage.
天啊  亚甘  我明了  你喜欢和枪保持亲密
Jeez, Gummy-drops, we get it. You like to get cozy with your guns.
不只是亲密  韦加先生  是人枪合一
Not just cozy, Mr. Welker. Conjoined.
这里很危险
This is a hot zone.
唏  云韦说他隶属哪个部门
Hey, what was that ministry Van Wyk said he was affiliated with?
南非野生动物联盟  为何这样问
South African Wildlife Federation. Why?
只是好奇
Just curious.
唏
Hey!
要兜风吗
You want a ride?
不  我们那边见
No, I'll see you over there.
哪边
See her where?
她邀请我参加一个部落跳舞集会
Oh, she invited me to some tribal dance thing.
晚上10黑占后不要出门
We move out at 2200 hours.
我建议你吃点东西  休息下
I suggest you grab some chow and get some rack time.
慢着  你对我实行宵禁
Wait. Are you giving me a curfew?
我不守宵禁  老爹  我是成年人
I don't do curfews, Pops. Okay? I'm an adult.
这是
But here's what I suggest you do.
我想你该进去了
I think you should go inside, right?
看下迷你吧有什么  看下你的退休计划
Check out the mini-bar situation. See how your 401 is doing.
我要和那惹火南非美女共度良宵
And I'll download the intel from the smokin' hot South African chick.
还有和土着共舞
And I am gonna dance with the natives.
唏
Hey!
过来
Come here!
唏  唏
Hey! Hey!
- 你来了  - 哇
- You made it. - Wow.
真热闹  是的
This is quite the rager. Yeah.
- 你们有酒吗  - 有
- You guys got a keg? - Yeah.
试试这个
Try this.
- 这是什么  - 勇气
- What's this? - Courage.
如何
And?
喝起来像牛尿
It tastes like cow piss.
- 还要吗  再来一口  - 我不要
- You want more? Try again. - No, I really don't.
这是什么
So, what is this?
斗士舞
This is a warrior dance.
我们的祖先猎杀巨蚌和闪电鸟
Our ancestors hunting the Inkanyamba and the impundulu.
那是什么
What's that?
闪电鸟  你们称之为艾巴
Impundulu. It's what you call the Ass Blaster.
- 艾巴  - 是的
- Ass Blaster. - Yes.
是的
Yes.
你让艾巴听起来还不错
Hey, you know, you make Ass Blaster sound good.
塔巴  我信不过那两个人
You know, Thaba, I'm really not sure about these guys.
尤其是那个卓华斯  我...
Especially this Travis guy. I mean...
我不喜欢他这样看我的娜蒂
I don't like the way he's looking at my Nandi.
她是你的吗
Is she your Nandi, now?
她可以是
Yeah, well, she could be.
祝你好运  老友
Good luck with that, bro.
我可以发梦吧
A guy can dream, right?
你能发梦我们有几瓶啤酒吗
Dream us up a couple of cold ones, would you?
几百瓶  老友
Hundreds, boet.
敬梦想
To dreams.
天啊
Jesus Christ!
好的
Okay.
你们称之为艾巴的
What you call the Ass Blaster, in our language,
在我们的语言里  意思是"燃烧鸟"
the word means "lightning bird."
闪电鸟是夜闲猎食者
The impundulu are nocturnal hunters.
他们前额有生物感应器  倚靠热能感应捕猎
They have bio-sensors on their foreheads and their hunt is based on heat signatures.
他们白天捕猎时  定位不大准确
If they hunt during the day, their targeting might be confused.
那么那些怪兽夜闲出没  在较低温度下捕猎
So, those freaks come out at night, so they can hunt their prey in cooler temps?
是的  他们就像吸血鬼
Yes, they're like vampires.
不  不  不
No, no, no!
他叼走了塔巴
It just took off with Thaba.
引擎的热力将他引来
It was attracted to the engine heat.
引擎是冷的  我们要救塔巴
The engine was cold. We gotta get Thaba.
我去拿装备
I'll get my gear.
哇  兄台  那是塔巴吗
Whoa, boet. Is that Thaba?
熄灭引擎
Kill the engine.
HPF  250隔热装备
HPF 250. Heat-blocking gear.
你有多一套给我吗
You got one of those ball gowns for me, princess?
如果你想隐藏热能  便打开冷气
Turn on the AC, if you wanna hide your heat signature.
好吧  猛人
Yeah, tough guy.
塔巴
Thaba.
唏
Hey.
塔巴
Thaba.
比起给美国人做保姆  我有更好的事情要做
I have better things to do than babysit Americans in Africa.
塔巴
Thaba!
坚持  我来了
Hold on, I got you.
顶  我没子弹了
Damn. I'm out.
来吧  兄台  老鬼  我们走吧
C'mon, boet. Come on, you old fart, let's get moving.
救我  兄台  救我  兄台
Help me, boet! Get this thing off me, boet! Help me, boet!
我击中了他的喷火屁股
I stuffed his blazing butt.
你就像蓝波
You're like freakin' Rambo.
我们走吧
Let's boogie.
出了什么事
Hey, what happened?
你在哪里
The question is where were you?
- 他和我一起  - 真的
- He was with me. - Really?
我要提醒你  医生
Well, here's some intel for you, Doc.
那些喷火怪已闯入你的保护区
Those fart-flaming sons of bitches have crossed your DMZ.
你要马上疏散所有人
You need to evacuate everyone, ASAP.
幸好你在  甘默先生
Thank God you're here, Mr. Gummer.
装上子弹  我们去追捕他们
All right, load every gun. We're going after them.
- 十分钟后出发  - 我去钩上笼子
- We leave in 10. - I'll hitch the lion cage.
美国佬  这是我的笼子  让我来
I don't think so, Yankee. My cage, my hitch.
唏  甘仔  等等  不要这样叫我
Hey, Gummy Bears, wait up. Don't call me that.
等等
Wait up.
第一  永远不要这样碰我
Number one, don't ever touch me like that again.
第二  永远不要这样碰我
Number two, don't ever touch me like that again.
明白了吗
You copy?
明白了
Yeah, I copy.
我没时闲给你摆甫士
I don't have the time to posture for your camera!
带你来是一个错误
This was a mistake, havin' you along.
你同样靠不住
Just another pimple on the ass of progress.
你得放松点
You need to chill out.
不要叫我放松  你擅离职守
Don't tell me to chill. You were AWOL.
现在我们有另一个人被杀  艾巴对我们发动全面袭击
Now, we've got another K.I.A. and a full-scale A.B. incursion to deal with.
你想有贡献
You want to make yourself useful?
帮他们疏散
Go help with the evac.
然后欢迎加入我  如果你自信能做到
Then, feel free to join in. Think you can manage that?
甘默先生  我想这个会对你有用
Mr. Gummer. I think you'll find this useful.
好东西
There is a God.
R5  弹夹已满
R5. Full banana clip.
我亲自调准星
I zeroed the scope myself.
你从哪里得来的
Where'd you get this?
你不必知道
You don't want to know.
我喜欢你的风格
I like your style. A-frickin'-men.
一个兽医为何会有一支机关枪
What's a veterinarian doing with a machine gun?
他们一定飞到河北岸了
They must've flown in north of the river.
艾巴不会飞  只会滑翔
Ass Blasters don't fly, they glide.
他们混合肠胃中几种
They mix several volatile gastrointestinal chemicals
可燃烧的化合物  藉助热力升空
that actually ignite, allowing them to achieve blast off.
他们放屁弹起自己  真有趣
They fart to take off? That's funny.
你听到了吗
Shh. Listen. You hear that?
黑背豺狼
Black-backed jackals.
食腐动物
Scavengers.
好吧  关掉引擎  我们去看看
All right. Take it ahead and kill the engine. We'll have a look.
你果然有备而来  甘默先生
You sure do come prepared, Mr. Gummer.
比臣是在悬崖对面的平地被杀
Basson was killed on that koppie, just underneath that cliff face.
看来我们找到艾巴的聚居地了
I think we have our Ass Blaster colony.
诱饵呢  我们是否要加热它
What about the bait? Don't we need to make it hot
好让艾巴看见
so these bastards can see it?
治运动伤
For sports injuries.
我们不需要肉
Forget the meat.
而需要热力
We need heat.
真开心
Happiness.
好吧  解开笼子
Okay, unhook the cage.
好的
Gotcha.
那是他吗
Is that it?
他们不是小儿科
Sure as hell ain't Mickey Mouse.
站在我身后  他们无法感应你们的热能
Stand behind me so he can't read your heat signature.
记着  甘默先生  活捉  不要杀
Remember, Mr. Gummer, capture, not kill.
放松  受死吧
Easy. Take your damn shot.
和我的宝贝打声招呼  贱人
Say hello to my dart, bitch.
不要慌张
Don't panic.
留在原位
Hold your position!
放松
Easy.
顶  我要离开这里
Screw that, I'm out of here!
不  留在我身边
No, stay with me, stay!
这就对了
That's right.
飞入我的十字准线吧
Fly right into my crosshairs,
你只屁股喷火的贱人
you fire-farting son of a bitch.
你杀不了我  我是非洲人
You can't kill me. I'm African.
火葬艾巴
Ass-Blast flambé.
你做了什么
What did you do?
你为何杀他
Why'd you kill it?
还有德亚
And Dreyer, too?
- 娜蒂  亚曼  - 怎么了
- Nandi, Amahle! - Yeah?
你留下这个
I think you left this in my truck.
- 谢谢  - 不客气
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
娜蒂  我们疏散后
Nandi. After we evacuate,
我想我该带你和亚曼  到一个安全的地方
I was thinking that maybe I should take you and Amahle somewhere safer.
我有很多事情要做  不能离开这里
There's so much work to do. I can't leave this place now.
这样的话  我也留下
In that case, I'm staying here.
陪你
With you.
我也是
Me, too.
真的
Really?
好吧  你们不要互射
You know what, try not to shoot each other, okay?
这说不通
This doesn't add up.
他无视火把
Ignored the thermal flare.
冲我们而来
Came directly at us.
保护巢穴  我明白了
Protecting the nest, weren't you? Roger that.
哪里有艾巴
Where there are Ass Blasters,
哪里就有圭布
there are Graboids.
对不起  我要你将那  能卖钱的玩意给我
Sorry, I'm going to have to take that little money-maker from you.
你想做什么
What're you doing?
赚大钱  把它递过来
Cashing in, hopefully. Why don't you hand that over?
我早该知你不怀好意
I should've known you were dirty.
那是我一生人最幸运的一天
Thought it was the luckiest day of my life.
我派德亚去捉猎豹幼患
I send Dreyer out to get a cheetah cub,
他却遇上一只会飞的食人兽
and he runs smack-bang into a flying carnivore.
你是谁
Who are you?
告诉你我不是谁
Let's start with who I'm not.
我不是南非野生动物部的人
I'm not with the South African Wildlife Ministry.
你这样做不会有好结果
This is not gonna end good for you.
当然有
Sure it will.
活的艾巴比猎豹仔
An Ass Blaster would've fetched 100 times
或犀牛角值钱一百倍
what a cheetah cub or a rhino horn would've.
死的就不是那么值钱了
Dead one, not nearly so much.
你是偷猎者
You're a common poacher?
我不介意这称呼
Morally, I'm okay with it.
但我介意你
You. Not so much.
好了  爬进笼里  否则我开枪射你
Now, get into the cage, or I'll shoot you in the stomach.
射我吧
Shoot me.
杀了我
Kill me.
但我不会进笼子
But you won't cage me.
还没结束
It ain't over
直至结束
till it's over.
真没用
Useless!
顶
Damn. Ow!
热
Hot.
自然的召唤
The call of nature.
几个世纪以来马赛人  都用尿液作为驱虫剂
The Maasai have been using urine as an insect repellent for centuries.
这可能是毕甘默
This may be the last will and testament
最后的遗嘱
of Mr. Bertram Gummer.
海德
Heather.
如果你还在外面
If you're still out there,
给HK41找个好的归宿
give the HK 41 a good home.
我想它
I miss it.
某程度上  也想你
And to some extent, you.
仆街云韦
Bastard Van Wyk.
如果我能活着出去
If I ever get out of here alive,
我不会放过你
I am coming for you.
真好味
Definitely an acquired taste.
还没结束吗
Is it over yet?
不  不  不
Oh, no, no, no.
杀掉这见鬼的狮子
Cue the freakin' lion.
我听不到你
I can't hear you.
两个王者
Two alphas.
同一共识
One understanding.
在食物链顶端  一定很孤独
It's lonely on top of the food chain. Huh?
噢  天啊  我们要认识彼此
Oh, God. We're getting to know one another.
总算可以遮阴了
Shade, at last.
顶  不  不
Shit! No. No!
不  不  不
No, no, no!
无胆鬼
Pussy!
我会打败你
I'll take you down.
虽然我放下了标枪
Thus I give up my spear.
我就是爬
I will claw my way
也要爬进你食道
down your gullet.
你选择冥想的时机不太好  老友
You picked a weird time to start meditating, dude.
- 你在这里做什么  - 我带你回动物园
- What the hell you doing here? - I'm taking you back to the zoo.
你开进了死亡区  正白痴
You drove straight into a kill zone, you moron.
你身后有一只圭布  快去高地
There's a Graboid right behind you. Get to high ground, now.
可能有点颠簸
This might get a bit bumpy.
坐稳了
Hang on to your frosting.
坐稳  毕
Hang on, Burt!
你上个停牌没有停
You missed that last stop sign.
余下的我走回去好了
I think I'll walk the rest of the way.
你不是喜欢户外吗
You wanted to be outdoors.
顶你  卓华斯
Damn you, Travis!
非洲滋味如何  毕
How's Africa taste, Burt?
来吧  开上岩石
Go! Get on the rocks. On the rocks!
开上岩石
The rocks! On the rocks!
顶
Oh, shit!
是我不好  你没事吧
My bad. You okay?
你几乎震断我体内每一根骨头
You damn near broke every bone in my body.
是的  但我也救了你一命
Yeah, but what does that have to do with me saving your life?
我发誓我看到圭布的行踪  可能是幻觉
I swear, I saw Graboid markers. I must be delirious.
不客气  老爹
You're welcome. Pops.
我叫你不要这样叫我
I told you not to call me that.
你怎么知道我在哪  千里眼
How'd you know where I was? Remote viewing.
我在国家安全局待过
Yeah, I spent a little time in the NSA.
笑  你上镜了
Smile, you're on candid camera.
对不起  我忘了带你的底裤
Sorry, I forgot your underwear.
我们被人出卖了
We've been betrayed.
云迪  你怎知道
Van Dick? How'd you know?
我知道他不像是典型的坏人
I knew the guy wasn't your typical, run-of-the-mill D-bag.
于是我暗中对他起底
So, I did a full, digital cavity search on him.
发现他是骗子
And guess what? Poser!
所谓的南非野生动物同盟
Yeah, that whole South African Wildlife Federation,
根本不存在
it's not even a thing.
他得到了一只圭布蛋  打算在黑市出售
He's got a Graboid egg, he intends to sell it on the black market,
后果将不堪设想
the implications of which are unfathomable.
- 你放屁  - 没有
- You fart? - No.
你闻到汽油味  是的
You smell gas? Affirmative.
油管裂了
Fuel line's busted.
好消息是我能修好它
Good news is I can fix it.
坏消息是我们没油了
Bad news is we're outta gas.
你没带备用油
You didn't bring a spare jerry can?
没有  毕  我没有带  因为我要赶来救你命
No, Burt, I forgot a spare jerry can 'cause I was rushing to save your ass.
那我们没话好说
And we've got no talk?
没有信号  没有无线网络  这丛林让你觉得宾至如归
No bars, no Wi-Fi in the bush. You must feel right at home.
我们要到高处搜寻手机信号
We got to get to high ground, so we can get a cell signal.
嗨
Hi.
那是什么
What was that?
你没事吧  亚曼  那里有些东西  妈妈
Are you okay, Nena? There's something out there, Mama.
我知道  宝贝
I know, baby, I know.
巴鲁提  带她回房好吗
Baruti. Baruti. Please take her to her room, now, okay?
来吧  亚曼  我们走吧
Come on, Amahle. Let's go.
给我你经常用来望远的  闲百某工具
Give me the spy thing you're always looking through.
- 望远镜  - 或单筒望远镜
- Oh! Field glasses? - Or binoculars.
什么都好  快给我
Yeah, whatever, Tommy Technical. Give 'em to me, let's go.
有发现吗
Anything?
- 顶  - 什么
- Oh, crap. - What?
我没看到云韦  但我看到他的陆地巡洋舰
There's no sign of Van Dick, but I got a bead on his Land Cruiser.
他一定躲在附近某处
He must be creeping around here somewhere.
怎么  你准备枪战  来吧
What, are you ready for a gun fight? Let's do this.
跑
Go, go!
毕
Burt, wait up.
这车很难转手了  这里有踪迹
There goes his trade-in value. Tracks here.
- 像蛇一样  - 是圭布吗
- Serpentine. - It's Graboid?
还有人类的
And human.
是云韦的  他在跑
Van Wyk's. He was running.
(白磷)
唏  毕  有些好东西给你
Ooh! Hey, Burt, got some war porn for you.
你也许喜欢这个
You might like that.
白磷  我喜欢
Phosphorus. I'm lovin' it.
我有扫把棍
I got dibs on the broomstick.
顶
Damn.
好极  子弹上膛
Oh, Yeah. Yes. Locked and loaded.
好了  冷静
Okay. Stay calm.
来吧
Come on.
受死吧
Take that.
妈妈  唏
Mama. Hey.
我真高兴你在这里  唏  你没事吧
I'm so glad you're here. Hey. You okay?
是的  大家都在
Yeah. Gang's all here.
他们来了  他们来了  他们来了  救命
They're coming! They're coming! They're coming! Help.
救我  他们来了  天啊
Help me! They're coming! Dear God!
他们来了  救命
They're coming! Help!
不要动
Freeze.
你在哪里
Where are you?
那是我的蛋  把我的蛋还给我
That's my egg. Give me back my egg.
快走  上岩石  上岩石
Move, get up on the rocks! On the rocks!
你在岩石上  他们无法攻击你
They can't reach you on the rocks. They can't get you up there.
留在岩石上
Stay on the rock.
不要动  留在那里
Don't move. Freeze there.
那是我的蛋
That's my egg.
这些圭布来势汹汹
These Grabs are on HGH.
开玩笑吧
Are you frickin' kidding me?
蛇触须从圭布身上分离出来
The tentacles have detached from the Graboid.
毕开始发威了
You're in the Burt zone now.
为何毕甘默不知道
Why is it the critical, need-to-know information
这一重要信息
never gets to Burt Gummer?
也许没人知道  没人知道
Well, maybe nobody knew. Nobody knew it?
没人知道这些仆街  可以自由活动了
Nobody knew the friggin' bastards have gone free range?
没事了
It's all right.
仆你个街  难以置信
Holy shit balls. Evolution run amok.
我不明白
I don't understand.
他们在非洲变种了  进化后变得更可怕
This African life cycle has mutated. It's much more evolved, more efficient.
艾巴在夜闲活动  蛇触须能从圭布身上分离
Nocturnal Ass Blasters, Grabbers that detach from the host.
史力在哪里
And where the hell are the Shriekers?
接下来会怎样  圭布会说话
What's next? Graboids that talk?
毕  冷静点  好吗  不要崩溃
Okay, Burt, keep it together, all right? Try not to have a breakdown.
让我们集中想一件事  为何他们袭击他
Let's just try to focus on one thing. Why were they zeroing in on that ice chest?
他们冲着蛋而来
They were going for the egg.
为了繁衍后代
Propagation of the species.
艾巴在保护他的圭布血脉
The Ass Blasters are protecting the Graboid bloodline.
你意思是那个山洞
So, you're sayin' there's some seriously gnarly shit in that cave.
是圭布的老巢
Like, it's really beast heavy, Graboid Ground Zero?
我们要进洞里  破坏那巢穴
We gotta get in that cave, destroy that nest.
我们不能让那些蛋卵孚化
We can't allow those eggs to hatch.
你留在这里  我进去
You sit tight. I'm goin' in.
何时起轮到你下令  从...收声  毕
Since when are you in command? Since... Shut up, Burt.
我不会听你废话  真的
I don't need your crap. Oh, really?
是啊  毕什么也不需要  除了谷类早餐和西梅汁
Yeah, Burt don't need nothin' except Fiber One cereal, prune juice,
卡其裤还有打怪兽
man khakis and a monster to hunt.
你有话要说  是的
You got somethin' to say to me? Yeah, I do.
你现在轻度中暑
You're suffering from a mild case of heat exhaustion
而且一把年纪
and a severe case of "getting too old for this crap."
把背心和枪给我
So, give me the vest and your flares.
- 我要进去  - 你说完了
- I'm goin' in. - Is that it?
说完了
That's it.
我为何仍觉得你在废话
Then why is the needle on my bullshit detector still in the red?
我不知道  你有信任问题  老友
I don't know. You got trust issues, man.
说真的  你需要看医生  把背心给我
Serious, you need therapy. Just give me the vest.
你手机有信号了吗
You got a signal on that phone, yet?
有一格
I have a bar.
交换  真的  你肯换  好的
Trade? Really, you're gonna barter? Okay.
三  二  一
Three, two, one.
遇到麻烦  你拔出
First sign of trouble, you pull the pin
白磷手榴弹上的顶针  然后逃命
on this white phosphorus grenade and you skedaddle.
明白吗  明白
Comprende? Comprende.
接下来交给我吧
I'll handle it from here.
我要承认  他真有种
He's got a pair, I'll give him that.
这太蠢了
This is retarded.
有话快讲  有屁快放
You're talking to me, so make it count.
比维先生  我是毕甘默  我遇到一点麻烦
Mr. Bravers, Burt Gummer here. I'm in a bit of pickle.
是啊  在野外这经常发生
Well, yeah. The bush can do that to you.
需要效劳吗
So, how can I help, boet?
我需要一罐油和一些军械
I need a jerry can of gas and some ammo.
为何不呢  你在哪里
Ah. Why the hell not? Where are you?
距离一条旧火车桥西北  大概三公里
About three clicks northwest of some old railroad bridge, modified for road use.
我知道那个地方
Ah, yeah, yeah. I know the spot.
我必须带重型武器
So, must I come heavy?
有其他办法
Is there any other way?
在边境战争中  我从一架  米格23上卸下几支火箭炮
Well, I've got a couple of rocket pods I took off a MiG-23 in the border war.
会不会太夸张  正好
It's too much? Just right.
来到非洲  我们会玩得很开心  看些比赛
Come to Africa. We'll have some laughs, see some game.
进入一个又深又黑的洞...
Go to a deep, dark, cavernous...
噢  天啊
Oh, my God.
不  不要再来
No. Not again!
你是一只丑陋的怪物
You are one ugly bitch.
去死吧
Suck on this!
有什么要报告  我们炸烂了圭布的老巢
Anything to report? Yeah. I think we hit the mother lode.
发生什么事  巴鲁提  我不知道
What's happening, Baruti? I don't know.
这些生物本该在夜间行动
I mean, these creatures are supposed to be nocturnal hunters.
为何变了
Why have they changed?
如非被迫  猎食者不会改变习性
Predators don't change their tactics unless they are forced to do that.
有些东西触发了这些攻击  动物总是冲着食物来
Something's triggered these attacks. Animals always go for the food source.
我不认为这是原因所在  这里有其他保护区
No, I don't think it's that. There are other reserves here.
- 那么说  他们冲着我们来  - 是的
- So, they're targeting us. - Yes.
确保所有枪装上子弹  准备好卡车
Make sure all of our weapons are loaded and the truck is ready.
我们要去村庄里
We're going to the village.
- 人多较安全  - 是的
- Safety in numbers. - Yeah.
那些蛋令他们火力全开
Those eggs have got themselves the full protection package.
我们收手
So, we punt?
没有这么快
Not so fast.
我们的支援到了
Our protection package has just arrived!
他们在那里
There they are.
不  我们行动吧
Oh, no. Let's call it!
我们激怒了领头怪兽
We pissed off the head worm?
(战猪)
关掉引擎
Shut it down.
到岩石上去
To the rocks, to the rocks!
来吧  回来
Come on, come on back!
不要放手
Hang on. Hang on.
来吧  进来  老友
Come on. Come here. Come back inside, man.
不要放手
Hold on!
查理
Charley?
Charley!
查理
Charley?
我们玩完了
This is a bag of dicks.
我们没子弹了  只能炸掉这洞
We're outta ammo and we have to blow that cave.
来吧  亚甘  不要放弃
Come on, Gums. Don't lose faith.
我们的处境的确很不妙
We are definitely F'ed up beyond all recognition.
但我们还有子弹  我只有这支烂鬼枪
But we are not out of ammo. All I got is this damn pop gun, that's it.
那支炮装满子弹  而且准备就绪
The bag is full, and it's ready to blow.
你要发挥想像力
Think outside the box.
- 噢  天啊  你是对的  - 是的
- Oh, my God. You're right. - Yeah.
这能和他们抗衡
That'll scramble a few eggs.
不  这会打沉那班怪物
Oh, no. That'll make a big frickin' omelet, is what that'll make.
怎样能到达直升机  而不被生吞
Now, how do we get to the chopper without gettin' eaten alive?
那边有一群牛
There's a herd of cattle out there.
和他们一起跑  能干扰他们对震波的探测
If we run with them, we can get lost in their seismic signatures.
什么  你的天才主意就是跑
What? That's your brilliant idea, to run?
"在非洲  每当太阳升起  你就要跑"
"When the sun rises in Africa, you better be running."
你准备好了吗  老鬼  你最好跟上
You ready for this, old man? You better step on it.
准备好了
Consider it stepped on.
就在前面
Not too far, now.
跑  跑  跑
Go, go, go, go!
借过  女士们  分开  分开
Out of my way, ladies. Break it up, break it up.
- 你去直升机那里  - 锁上门
- You get to the helo. - You lock it up.
耶  放松  他会回来
Yeah! Easy, hoss. She'll be back.
好了  让我们煎几只蛋吧
Right. Let's poach some eggs.
- 炒蛋  - 对
- Scramble. - My bad.
这些火箭筒每边能搭载16支炮  看来他装了10支
Hello. These MiG pods hold 16 rockets each. Looks like he loaded 10.
这应该足够了  会不会滥杀无辜
This is gonna ring their bells. It's a bit of overkill, don't you think?
如果你要开杀戒  就要杀个片甲不留
If you're gonna give 'em the horn, give 'em the horn.
好了  听够60年代了
All right. All right, enough of the '60s.
唏  我喜欢那首歌  拜托  图派在哪
Hey, I like that song. Come on, where's the Tupac?
毕才不喜欢怀旧嬉皮士  关于爱情自由的东西
Burt doesn't love the old hippy-dippy, free-love stuff, does he?
带我回去  回去哪里
Takes me back. Back to where?
回到我们见面前
Back before I met your sorry ass.
回到佛罗里达的枪展
Back to a gun show in Florida?
你知佛州什么
What do you know about Florida?
我们在浪费时闲
We're burnin' daylight.
好了  激光瞄准  锁定目标
All right. Laser designated. Locked on target.
天啊
Holy shit balls!
顶
Oh, yeah!
疯子
Psycho.
怎么回事  天啊
What the hell? Jesus.
怎么回事  我以为你死了  老友
What the hell? I thought you were dead, man!
生吞  我被怪物生吞了
Swallowed. Swallowed by that wide broad.
她之前吃得太多  还没有排便
She was about 10 meals ahead and 20 craps behind.
于是将我吐出来了
So, she spat me out.
吐出来
Spat you out?
我给她的肚子瘙痒
Well, I tickled the insides of her belly a little bit.
我也这样做过  老友
Been there, done that, my man.
怪物回来了  我们走吧
The bitch is back. Let's get outta here.
扣上安全带  各位  来吧  我们走吧  关上门
Buckle up, boys. Come on, let's go. Lock it up, lock it up.
好了  我们走吧
Okay, let's go.
- 我们走吧  - 来吧  来吧
- Let's go. - Come on, come on, come on.
来吧  来吧
Come, come, come, come on.
离我近点  亚曼  好吗
Stay close, Amahle. Stay close, okay?
他们来了
They're here.
好吧  我们要上你的卡车
Okay. All we need to do is get to your truck.
离我近点
Stay close.
又上屋顶
Again with the roof?
我喜欢这样大胆的巴鲁提
I like this badass Baruti.
来吧  亚曼  到后面去
Come. Come, Amahle. Come on, get in the back.
好孩子
Good girl.
顶
Shit!
他无法通过那水泥路
It couldn't make it through the concrete slab.
他转向了
Okay, it's turning around.
我有个办法
I've got an idea.
好了  留在这里  宝贝
All right. Stay here, baby, okay?
给我个火机
Give me a light, give me a light.
好了  谢谢
There you go. Thanks.
我们走吧
Let's go.
- 多谢支援  - 不客气  兄台
- Thanks for the gas. - No worries, boet.
听着  我要去祖鲁兰救火了
Hey, look, I've gotta go and fight a fire in Zululand,
我条女等得不耐烦
and my girl's running on fumes.
- 如果你需要帮忙... - 吹号角找你
- So, if you need me... - I can reach you on the horn.
我感觉你需要这个
I've got a feeling you're gonna be needing this.
FN  MAG  够经典
An FN MAG. Classic.
这宝贝火力很猛
She packs a punch, that baby.
她是你的了  多谢  兄台
She's all yours. Thanks. Boet.
不停地跑
Always be running. Yeah.
不要停下来  兄台  永远不要
Never stop running, boet. Never!
我们来谈谈佛罗里达吧
Let's talk about Florida.
阳光之州  到处是美女
Sunshine State. Lotta ladies.
我问的是  关于我和佛罗里达  你知道什么
I'm askin' what you know about me and Florida.
我知道你在那里的时候  去了一场感恩死亡
I know that you went to a Grateful Dead concert once
演唱会
when you were there.
你怎么知道  这是40年前的事了
How could you possibly know that? That was 40 years ago.
我还知道你和谁去
Pretty sure I know who you went with.
你知姬丝敏什么
What do you know about Jasmine?
嬉皮士  吸白粉  模特儿
Flower child meets heroin chic. Model.
讨厌的士高  喜欢罕醉克斯
Hated disco. Loved Hendrix.
你在卖你爸的旧枪  她在停车场里
You were selling your dad's old guns. She was in the parking lot.
烧她的胸罩  极左遇上极右
Burning her bra. Far left meets far right.
你们共度了一夜
They spend the night.
真浪漫  毕
Love's a bitch, huh, Burt?
她和你什么关系
Who is she to you?
大部分时闲我叫她"妈"
I call her "Mom" most of the time.
很令你意外吧
Well, that's gotta stir up some shit, right? Huh?
你意思是  你和我是...没错  父子
You mean, you and me are... That's right. Bloodlines.
你感受到了吗
Feel the theme happenin', here?
- 不  - 是的
- No. - Yes.
这不可能  你来告诉我
No. Impossible. You're tellin' me.
我不相信  你不可能是我孩子
I don't believe it. There's no way you're my offspring.
什么  你这样说太过分  你以为你比我好
What? Well, that's a dick thing to say? What, do you think you're better than me?
我只是...看看你
I just don't... I mean... Crud. Look at you!
是啊  看看我
Yeah, look at me.
我怎么可能是毕甘默的儿子  他可是个大人物
How could I be the son of Burt Gummer? A man of such towering importance.
你知道吗  算了
You know what? Forget it.
我们不必在这演真情
We don't have to do this whole Dr. Phil thing, okay?
当务之急是在非洲逃出生天
Let's just survive this African worm invasion,
事情完结后我们不必再联络  这样行了吧
and we'll go back to never speaking to each other again. Cool?
仆街
Son of a bitch!
我们赶紧走吧
Let's get outta here.
走吧
Let's boogie.
顶
Damn it!
他缠住了车胎  有枪就要用
Grabber's got us hooked! You've got a gun. Use it.
耶  老友
Yeah, dawg!
我要做个亲子鉴定
I want a paternity test.
这是什么  我找到的
What's this? I found it.
- 亚曼  - 怎么回事
- Amahle. - What's going on?
我想我知我们为何受攻击了
I think I know why we're under attack.
他们去哪里  村庄里
Where would they go? The village.
人多较安全  我们走吧
Safety in numbers. Let's go.
留在车里  宝贝
Stay in the car, baby, okay?
(摇篮石杂货铺)
娜蒂
Nandi!
来吧  我们走吧
Come on. Come on! Let's go!
亚曼  亚曼
Amahle? Amahle?
Amahle? Amahle.
- 亚曼  - 亚曼
- Amahle! - Amahle!
妈
Mom!
没有地震活动
No seismic activity.
卓华斯  看  亚曼  在你身后
Travis, look! Amahle, behind you!
天啊  不  回到卡车上
God, no! No, no. Off the ground and on the truck!
- 不  她是我孩子  不  - 我们走吧
- No, she's my child. No! - Let's go.
- 没事的  宝贝  - 没事的  我们到那边等
- It's gonna be okay, honey. - It's okay. Wait right there.
跑  跑  跑
Go, go, go!
- 没事的  宝贝  - 坚持
- It's gonna be okay, honey. - Hold on!
我来射他  不  可能会伤这女孩
Let me get a shot on it. No, no, no. We can't risk hitting the girl.
她篮子里有什么  我想是一只怪兽蛋
What does she have in that basket? I think she's got an Inkanyamba egg.
- 这蛋是他们最后的血脉  - 你何出此言
- That egg is the last of the bloodline. - Why do you say that?
因为我们炸了他们的老巢
Because we blew up their nest.
听着  我们有蛋做人质
Look, we have a hostage situation.
只有蛋在她手上  他们就不敢碰她
They're not gonna touch her as long as she has the egg.
- 有多少只怪物  - 一只
- What's the worm count?  - One.
这仆街是冲着蛋来
And the queen bitch is comin' for that egg.
唏  唏  唏
Hey. Hey, hey, hey.
- 看到那个吗  - 看到
- You see what I see? - Yeah.
好吧  我们其中一人引开他  另一人去救那孩子
Okay. One of us is gonna be bait and one of us has gotta snatch the kid.
- 谁去  - 我去救她
- Who's it gonna be? - I'll get her.
- 等着  宝贝  - 我们行动吧
- Hold on, baby. - Let's go.
不要动
Stand still!
巴鲁提
Baruti!
卓华斯  这边  扔过来
Travis, here. Throw it!
- 没事了  - 你救到她了
- It's okay. It's okay. - You got her, you got her.
在你身后
Behind you!
- 我有个主意  - 说吧
- I think I have an idea. - Shoot.
亚曼总是用她的电夹来捉虫
Amahle always uses her earthworm zapper to catch worms.
我们可以做一个大型的
We can build one on a much larger scale.
我们有虫了  该用什么来做电夹
We have the worm. What do you suggest we use for the zap?
闪电
The lightning.
可以利用油田的棍棒  用电线将它们绑起
We can use the pile rods from the drill rig and wire them together.
我们知道打雷闪电的时闲  对不对
You can set your watch to the lightning, right?
是的  距离现在还有13分钟
Yes, and right now we've got 13 minutes.
希望新娘会准时出现
Let's hope the bride doesn't get cold feet.
怎么回事
What's goin' on?
- 你能继续引开她吗  - 我会尽力
- Can you keep her busy? - I can try.
我们够运的话  他会跟着你的震波
If we're lucky, she'll follow your seismic signature.
引他到河边  等我信号再引他回来
Send them to the river and bring them back on my signal.
- 你的信号  - 我会射火焰箭
- Your signal? - I'll send up a flare.
放一点给我
Give me some slack.
游戏开始  卓华斯
Game on, Travis.
来吧  怪物
Come on, tube snake!
他们正过来  天啊  好吧
Come on. They're headed our way. Goodness, okay.
跑  跑  跑
Go, go, go, go!
来吧  不管你在哪
Come on, wherever you are.
上屋顶
On the roof.
乖仔
Sonny boy!
他来了
Here it comes!
结束了  宝贝  我们走吧
It's over, baby. Come, let's go.
我全身都是虫尸
I just got wormed.
唏
Hey.
给你
Here.
不  我知这是非洲  但我不会猎杀的东西
Ooh. Yeah, no, I know this is Africa, but I'm not gonna eat what I just killed.
- 谢谢你  - 好吧
- Thank you. - Okay.
卓华斯  我想谢谢你
Well, Travis, I just wanted to say thank you for everything.
你内心深处是个好男人
You're a good man. Deep down there.
表面上不是
What, it's not on the surface?
大部分时闲不是  要深入认识你才知
It rarely ever is. You've gotta dig deep.
再见
See ya.
亚曼
Amahle!
今天做得好
Good work today.
是的
Yeah.
你也是
You, too.
毕氏火车下一站到哪里
So, what's the next stop on the Burt train?
回到没人关心的内华达
More Who-The-Hell-Cares, Nevada?
那是我的家
It's home.
你要去哪里  我不知道
Where you goin'? I don't know.
也许回佛罗里达
Probably back to Florida.
好吧  你保重
Okay. You take care, you hear?
唏  等等
Hey, wait a minute.
我的品牌呢  什么
What about my career? What about it?
我们有协议在先
We had a deal.
你说要帮它长远发展  打造甘默品牌
You said you were gonna take the long view, build the Gummer brand.
你说会帮我解决问题
Said you were gonna fix me.
你不需要人解决问题  老爹
You don't need fixin', Pops.
来吧  我们还要到弗雷斯诺打妖精
Now, come on. We got a gremlin to catch in Fresno.
老爹
Pops.
(生存者)
(毕甘默与卓华斯韦加)
我叫毕甘默  我有很多外号
My name is Burt Gummer, and I've been called many things.
枪狂  怪兽猎人  末日预备者
Gun enthusiast, monster-hunter, doomsday-prepper.
我拒绝这些标签
I reject all these labels.
我是生存者
What I am is a survivalist.
我是卓华斯韦加
And I'm Travis B. Welker.
人们说我是忍者摄影师  喜欢追求刺激
I've been accused of being a ninja photographer, an adrenaline junkie,
喜欢勾引22岁妹妹仔
and hitting on hot 22-year-olds.
我承认
I'm guilty on all accounts.
我喜欢这些标签  并以它们为生
I embrace these labels, and I live by them.
我们携手合作  接受离奇  致命  古怪的任务
And together, we're taking on the bizarre, the deadly, the weird.
这是一份肮脏的工作
It's a dirty job.
但很性感
But dirty guys are sexy.
(这位是父亲)
我们解开了生存密码
We've cracked the code of survival.
我们是所有可怕  古怪  爬行生物的克星
We are the cure that ails anything crittery, creepy or crawly.
(这位是儿子)
我们是
We are the knockout punch to the shadowy world of monsters.
跑  跑  跑
Go, go, go!
(这是刺激所在)
我不知你将释放的是什么
I don't know what the hell you unleashed in there.
如果你需要我们帮忙对付  任何在你地板下作怪的生物
So, if you need us for anything that goes bang in the night or fluff under your floor...
- 在那边  - 小心背后
- It's over here! - Watch your back!
或者只是...
Or just...
...吹号角找我们
...reach us on the horn.
记着  生存和生命从这里开始
And remember, survival and life starts here.
(生存者)
(毕甘默与卓华斯韦加)
(准备就绪)
(前往危险地区)